

# Simon Pelletier

CEP | M.A.Sc. Candidate Mechanical Engineering

@ simon.pelletier.5@etsmtl.net

in SimPelletierPouliot

SimPelletier

Link to Online Resume

## About me

I am a mechanical engineering candidate with a specialization in mechanical design. I possess particular expertise in the use of Python and open-source libraries for the design and validation of mechanical structures, which I have applied to my master's project.

My experience includes mechanical design of composite structures, manufacturing processes, tooling and machine element design. Additionally, I have a strong understanding of cable mechanics, which I acquired as part of my master's research.

## Skills

Mechanical Design (SolidWorks, Catia, Fusion360)

Programming (Python, Numba, Latex)

Structural Engineering (Ansys APDL, Altair, Fatigue)

Data Analysis (Numpy, Pandas, Sk-learn)

Computer Vision (OpenCV)

Scientific Visualization (VTK, Paraview)

French\*6 English\*4 Spanish\*3 Solution-Oriented\*5

(\*) - The skill scale is from 0 (Fundamental Awareness) to 6 (Expert).

### Education

Since 2022

#### M.A.Sc. candidate in Mechanical Engineering

To École de Technologie Supérieure (ETS)

Comprehensive mechanical modeling of cables under cyclic loading for service life prediction.

- 3D reconstruction of cable internal wire paths from computed tomography data using image processing (OpenCV).
- Macro-scale modeling of internal cable structures using homogenization approaches (*Python, APDL*).
- Wire-level modeling of a braided structure inside cable outer layers with several million contact points.
- Analysis of contact interaction data using open-source 3D scientific visualization tools (VTK).

#### Win-Spr 2020 Abroad Studies

At Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya (UPC)

2016 to 2020 B.Sc. in Mechanical Engineering

From École de Technologie Supérieure (ETS)

2013 to 2016 College in Mechanical Engineering

From Cégep Lévis-Lauzon

### **Experience**

#### 2022 to 2024 Practical class teacher for MEC528 course

Part-time

École de Technologie Supérieure (ETS)

- Synthesize concepts related to machine elements and fatigue.
- · Carry out classroom and laboratory exercises.

#### 2020 to 2022 CEP Project Manager

Centre de développement des composites du Québec (CDCQ)

 Design of tooling and structural composite parts for high-performance and lightweight solutions.

#### Sum 2019 Mechanical Designer

Rocky Mountain Bicycles

- · Design of reliability test benches for electric motor components.
- Implementation of an electric motor efficiency bench test.
- · Post-processing of test data.
- · Development of test procedures.

#### Sum-Fal 2017 Mechanical Designer

Internship

Internship

Centre de développement des composites du Québec (CDCQ)

- Design of tooling and structural composite parts.
- Implementation of a large-capacity FDM 3D printer.
- · Design of a nylon in-situ curing machine.

#### Sum 2016 **Draftsman**

Les Équipements Marki

- · Industrial machinery design and modeling.
- · Welding and assembly.

## Projects<sup>®</sup>

Spr 2022

#### **Custom Linear FEA Program of Composite Beams and Plates**

École de Technologie Supérieure (ETS-SYS806)

- Orthotropic properties derived from the Classical Laminate Theory.
- · Beam element formulation based on Timoshenko beam theory.
- Plate element formulation based on Reissner-Mindlin theory.
- Validated with Ansys<sup>®</sup> software using the ACP module.

#### Win-Spr 2020 Design of a Bicycle Cable Disc Brake 3

Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya (UPC)

#### 2016 to 2018 Participation in the Student Project C-Class Catamaran Q

École de Technologie Supérieure (ETS)

#### Spr 2016 Design and Manufacture of a Nylon Ropes Machine Cutter 3

From Cégep Lévis-Lauzon

- · Design and manufacture of the prototype.
- Program an Arduino board for system operation and user interface.

### Awards

2023 Recipient of an Excellence Scholarship (ETS).

2018 & 2020 Recipient of Two Scholarships from Private Companies to Encour-

age Career Choice (ETS).

2015 Recipient of Three Grants for an Entrepreneurial Project.

2013 Medal Recipient of The "Lieutenant-gouverneur du Québec".

(③) - Link Available

References Upon Request